<appendix id="credits">
 <title>Credits and Legalities</title>

 <para>Yes, we all love those legalities, don't we? Without further ado, here's (hopefully) all of the credits.</para>

 <note><para>If you feel left out, be assured that it wasn't on purpose. Just mail me and I'll add you to the
  list.</para></note>

 <sect1 id="credits-expat">
  <title>&lt;eXpat/&gt;</title>
  <titleabbrev>expat</titleabbrev>

  <para>This software relies on the expat library for parsing XML files, which is released under the following license
   terms.</para>

  <para>Copyright (c) 1998, 1999, 2000 Thai Open Source Software Center Ltd and Clark Cooper</para>
  <para>Copyright (c) 2001, 2002, 2003, 2004, 2005, 2006 Expat maintainers.</para>
  <para>Permission is hereby granted, free of charge, to any person obtaining a copy of this software and associated
   documentation files (the "Software"), to deal in the Software without restriction, including without limitation the
   rights to use, copy, modify, merge, publish, distribute, sublicense, and/or sell copies of the Software, and to
   permit persons to whom the Software is furnished to do so, subject to the following conditions:</para>
  <para>The above copyright notice and this permission notice shall be included in all copies or substantial portions
   of the Software.</para>
  <para>THE SOFTWARE IS PROVIDED "AS IS", WITHOUT WARRANTY OF ANY KIND, EXPRESS OR IMPLIED, INCLUDING BUT NOT LIMITED
   TO THE WARRANTIES OF MERCHANTABILITY, FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE AND NONINFRINGEMENT. IN NO EVENT SHALL THE
   AUTHORS OR COPYRIGHT HOLDERS BE LIABLE FOR ANY CLAIM, DAMAGES OR OTHER LIABILITY, WHETHER IN AN ACTION OF CONTRACT,
   TORT OR OTHERWISE, ARISING FROM, OUT OF OR IN CONNECTION WITH THE SOFTWARE OR THE USE OR OTHER DEALINGS IN THE
   SOFTWARE.</para>

  <itemizedlist>
   <listitem><para><ulink url="http://expat.sourceforge.net/">Expat Homepage</ulink></para></listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
 </sect1>

 <sect1 id="credits-contributors">
  <title>Contributors</title>
  <titleabbrev>Contributors</titleabbrev>

  <para>This is in no particular order and might in fact accidentally omit one person or another. If you feel left
   out, please say so so i can add ya :)</para>

  <itemizedlist>
   <listitem><para>KKtm</para></listitem>
   <listitem><para>DieselPower</para></listitem>
   <listitem><para>AidanJT</para></listitem>
   <listitem><para>nikolavp</para></listitem>
   <listitem><para>niick</para></listitem>
   <listitem><para>teppic</para></listitem>
   <listitem><para>haader</para></listitem>
   <listitem><para>olof</para></listitem>
   <listitem><para>lonn</para></listitem>
   <listitem><para>yoyo</para></listitem>
   <listitem><para>Lloeki</para></listitem>
   <listitem><para>Janax</para></listitem>
   <listitem><para>shaumux</para></listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
 </sect1>

 <sect1 id="credits-authors">
  <title>Authors/Developers</title>
  <titleabbrev>Authors</titleabbrev>

  <para>Not many current "real" developers around, but since this is the credits section, might as well list us all.
   :D</para>

  <para>The order is straight from the "AUTHORS" file shipped with the XML modules, so it's pretty much the order in
   which people joined up.</para>

  <itemizedlist>
   <listitem><para>mdeininger/jyujin: Magnus Deininger, dma05@web.de</para></listitem>
   <listitem><para>rmh3093: Ryan Hope, rmh3093@gmail.com</para></listitem>
   <listitem><para>creidiki: Leonardo Valeri Manera, l.valerimanera@gmail.com</para></listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
 </sect1>

</appendix>
