<!DOCTYPE refentry PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook V4.1//EN">
<refentry>
 <refentryinfo>
  <date>2008-02-24</date>
  
  <authorgroup>
   <author>
    <firstname>Magnus</firstname>
    <surname>Deininger</surname>
   </author>
  </authorgroup>
  <copyright>
   <year>2008</year>
   <holder>Magnus Deininger</holder>
  </copyright>
 </refentryinfo>
 
 <refmeta>
  <refentrytitle><application>einit-log</application></refentrytitle>
  <manvolnum>8</manvolnum>
  <refmiscinfo>einit-log-0.40.0</refmiscinfo>
 </refmeta>
 
 <refnamediv>
  <refname>
   <application>einit-log</application>
  </refname>
  <refpurpose>retrieve log data from einit</refpurpose>
 </refnamediv>
 
 <refsynopsisdiv>
  <cmdsynopsis>
   <command>einit-log</command>
   <arg>-a <replaceable class="parameter">address</replaceable></arg>
   <arg><group><arg>-h</arg><arg>--help</arg></group></arg>
   <arg><group><arg>-f</arg><arg>--follow</arg></group></arg>
   <arg><group><arg>-r</arg><arg>--replay-only</arg></group></arg>
  </cmdsynopsis>
 </refsynopsisdiv>
 
 <refsect1>
  <refsect1info>
   <date>2008-02-24</date>
  </refsect1info>
  <title>DESCRIPTION</title>
  <para>
   <command>einit-log</command> is a simple command-line utility that may be used to extra log data from
   a running einit core. It simply connects to einit, fetches the event log and displays it.
  </para>
 </refsect1>
 
 <refsect1>
  <title>OPTIONS</title>
  <variablelist>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>-a <replaceable class="parameter">address</replaceable></term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      The 9P2000 address to connect to. The default is <emphasis>unix!/dev/einit-9p</emphasis>.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>-h</term>
    <term>--help</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Display help screen and exit.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>-r</term>
    <term>--replay-only</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Replay the event log, then exit. This is the default behaviour.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>-f</term>
    <term>--follow</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Follow the event log, that is, replay first, then stay connected and wait for updates.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>
 </refsect1>
 
 <refsect1>
  <title>ENVIRONMENT</title>
  <para>
   Some command line options may be used to set defaults for this programme.
  </para>
  <variablelist>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>EINIT_9P_ADDRESS=<replaceable>address</replaceable></term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Equivalent to the -a option. The command-line option overrides this variable.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>
 </refsect1>
 
 <refsect1>
  <title>USAGE</title>
  <para>
   The main use of this programme is to be able to retrieve notice logs and bootup messages
   from einit's core. Usually this is done via <command>einit-log&gt;logfile</command>.
  </para>
  <para>
   <command>einit-log --follow</command> is also quite useful, since it allows trying something
   and seeing immediate results in the event log. An instance of this command is usually spawned
   by einit on tty11.
  </para>
 </refsect1>
 
 <refsect1>
  <title>FILES</title>
  <variablelist>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>/dev/einit-9p</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      The unix socket that is used (by default) for the 9p2000(.u) IPC.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>
 </refsect1>
 
 <refsect1>
  <title>BUGS</title>
  <para>Please send bug reports to the <emphasis>issue tracker on einit.org</emphasis>.</para>
  <para>
   Remember that this is BETA software: avoid using this on mission-critical systems.
  </para>
 </refsect1>
 
 <refsect1>
  <title>SEE ALSO</title>
  <para>einit(8), einit-feedback(8), einit-sysvd(8)</para>
  <para><ulink url="http://einit.org/">The official project website</ulink></para>
 </refsect1>
 
 <refsect1>
  <title>AUTHOR</title>
  <para>
   Written by Magnus Deininger <email>mdeininger@jyujin.de</email>.
  </para>
 </refsect1>
 
 <refsect1>
  <title>COPYRIGHT</title>
  <para>(C) 2008 Magnus Deininger, All rights reserved.</para>
  <para>Redistribution and use in source and binary forms, with or without modification,
   are permitted provided that the following conditions are met:</para>
  <para>
   <itemizedlist>
    <listitem><para>Redistributions of source code must retain the above copyright notice,
      this list of conditions and the following disclaimer.</para></listitem>
    <listitem><para>Redistributions in binary form must reproduce the above copyright notice,
      this list of conditions and the following disclaimer in the documentation
      and/or other materials provided with the distribution.</para></listitem>
    <listitem><para>Neither the name of the project nor the names of its contributors may be
      used to endorse or promote products derived from this software without
      specific prior written permission.</para></listitem>
   </itemizedlist>
  </para>
  <para>
   THIS SOFTWARE IS PROVIDED BY THE COPYRIGHT HOLDERS AND CONTRIBUTORS "AS IS" AND
   ANY EXPRESS OR IMPLIED WARRANTIES, INCLUDING, BUT NOT LIMITED TO, THE IMPLIED
   WARRANTIES OF MERCHANTABILITY AND FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE ARE
   DISCLAIMED. IN NO EVENT SHALL THE COPYRIGHT OWNER OR CONTRIBUTORS BE LIABLE FOR
   ANY DIRECT, INDIRECT, INCIDENTAL, SPECIAL, EXEMPLARY, OR CONSEQUENTIAL DAMAGES
   (INCLUDING, BUT NOT LIMITED TO, PROCUREMENT OF SUBSTITUTE GOODS OR SERVICES;
   LOSS OF USE, DATA, OR PROFITS; OR BUSINESS INTERRUPTION) HOWEVER CAUSED AND ON
   ANY THEORY OF LIABILITY, WHETHER IN CONTRACT, STRICT LIABILITY, OR TORT
   (INCLUDING NEGLIGENCE OR OTHERWISE) ARISING IN ANY WAY OUT OF THE USE OF THIS
   SOFTWARE, EVEN IF ADVISED OF THE POSSIBILITY OF SUCH DAMAGE.
  </para>
 </refsect1>
</refentry>