<!DOCTYPE refentry PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook V4.1//EN">
<refentry>
 <refentryinfo>
  <date>2008-02-24</date>

  <authorgroup>
   <author>
    <firstname>Magnus</firstname>
    <surname>Deininger</surname>
   </author>
  </authorgroup>
  <copyright>
   <year>2008</year>
   <holder>Magnus Deininger</holder>
  </copyright>
 </refentryinfo>

 <refmeta>
  <refentrytitle><application>einit-feedback</application></refentrytitle>
  <manvolnum>8</manvolnum>
  <refmiscinfo>einit-feedback-0.40.0</refmiscinfo>
 </refmeta>

 <refnamediv>
  <refname>
   <application>einit-feedback</application>
  </refname>
  <refpurpose>display feedback data from einit</refpurpose>
 </refnamediv>

 <refsynopsisdiv>
  <cmdsynopsis>
   <command>einit-feedback</command>
   <arg>-a <replaceable class="parameter">address</replaceable></arg>
  </cmdsynopsis>
 </refsynopsisdiv>

 <refsect1>
  <refsect1info>
   <date>2008-02-24</date>
  </refsect1info>
  <title>DESCRIPTION</title>
  <para>
   <command>einit-feedback</command> is a small curses-based helper application that is used to display
   all the feedback data einit provides. It is usually run by einit on tty9, but it may be run by any member
   of the einit group in any terminal they favour.
  </para>
 </refsect1>

 <refsect1>
  <title>OPTIONS</title>
  <variablelist>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>-a <replaceable class="parameter">address</replaceable></term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      The 9P2000 address to connect to. The default is <emphasis>unix!/dev/einit-9p</emphasis>.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>
 </refsect1>

 <refsect1>
  <title>ENVIRONMENT</title>
  <para>
   Some command line options may be used to set defaults for this programme.
  </para>
  <variablelist>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>EINIT_9P_ADDRESS=<replaceable>address</replaceable></term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Equivalent to the -a option. The command-line option overrides this variable.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>
 </refsect1>

 <refsect1>
  <title>USAGE</title>
  <para>
   Simply launch this programme on your favourite tty and it will replay the event log from the
   core. The resulting output is the same as that on tty9, so you do not need to switch there just
   to get einit feedback.
  </para>
  <para>Keymap:</para>
  <variablelist>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>UP/DOWN arrow keys</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Disable the 'auto scroll mode' and scroll up and down.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>a</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Restore the 'auto scroll mode', which is the default mode.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>j/k</term>
    <term>p/n</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      vi-ish/emacs-ish bindings for the UP/DOWN keys' actions.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>shift+L</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Toggle displaying the core's notice messages.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>
 </refsect1>

 <refsect1>
  <title>FILES</title>
  <variablelist>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>/dev/einit-9p</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      The unix socket that is used (by default) for the 9p2000(.u) IPC.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>
 </refsect1>

 <refsect1>
  <title>BUGS</title>
  <para>Please send bug reports to the <emphasis>issue tracker on einit.org</emphasis>.</para>
  <para>
   Remember that this is BETA software: avoid using this on mission-critical systems.
  </para>
 </refsect1>

 <refsect1>
  <title>SEE ALSO</title>
  <para>einit(8), einit-log(8), einit-sysvd(8)</para>
  <para><ulink url="http://einit.org/">The official project website</ulink></para>
 </refsect1>

 <refsect1>
  <title>AUTHOR</title>
  <para>
   Written by Magnus Deininger <email>mdeininger@jyujin.de</email>.
  </para>
 </refsect1>

 <refsect1>
  <title>COPYRIGHT</title>
  <para>(C) 2008 Magnus Deininger, All rights reserved.</para>
  <para>Redistribution and use in source and binary forms, with or without modification,
   are permitted provided that the following conditions are met:</para>
  <para>
   <itemizedlist>
    <listitem><para>Redistributions of source code must retain the above copyright notice,
      this list of conditions and the following disclaimer.</para></listitem>
    <listitem><para>Redistributions in binary form must reproduce the above copyright notice,
      this list of conditions and the following disclaimer in the documentation
      and/or other materials provided with the distribution.</para></listitem>
    <listitem><para>Neither the name of the project nor the names of its contributors may be
      used to endorse or promote products derived from this software without
      specific prior written permission.</para></listitem>
   </itemizedlist>
  </para>
  <para>
   THIS SOFTWARE IS PROVIDED BY THE COPYRIGHT HOLDERS AND CONTRIBUTORS "AS IS" AND
   ANY EXPRESS OR IMPLIED WARRANTIES, INCLUDING, BUT NOT LIMITED TO, THE IMPLIED
   WARRANTIES OF MERCHANTABILITY AND FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE ARE
   DISCLAIMED. IN NO EVENT SHALL THE COPYRIGHT OWNER OR CONTRIBUTORS BE LIABLE FOR
   ANY DIRECT, INDIRECT, INCIDENTAL, SPECIAL, EXEMPLARY, OR CONSEQUENTIAL DAMAGES
   (INCLUDING, BUT NOT LIMITED TO, PROCUREMENT OF SUBSTITUTE GOODS OR SERVICES;
   LOSS OF USE, DATA, OR PROFITS; OR BUSINESS INTERRUPTION) HOWEVER CAUSED AND ON
   ANY THEORY OF LIABILITY, WHETHER IN CONTRACT, STRICT LIABILITY, OR TORT
   (INCLUDING NEGLIGENCE OR OTHERWISE) ARISING IN ANY WAY OUT OF THE USE OF THIS
   SOFTWARE, EVEN IF ADVISED OF THE POSSIBILITY OF SUCH DAMAGE.
  </para>
 </refsect1>
</refentry>